Okay, so we've got a metric buttload of
social reform movements that occurred
from 1800 to 1848 and it's time to talk
about them. So if you're ready to get
them brain cows milked temperance style,
let's get to it. Okay, now really this
video is just an extension of my videos
on the market revolution and the second
great awakening. And that's because
without those two massive society
changing developments, much of the
social reform that I'm floapping my
mouth hole about would not have
occurred. So keep that tucked away in
your brain folds cuz it's important.
Okay, so let's spend some time with
these reformers and their multitudinous
movements. And we'll start by
considering new voluntary organizations
that sought to change society and
individual behavior in most cases apart
from government intervention. And
there's no better place to begin than
with the temperance movement, which
aimed to curb or eliminate the
manufacturing consumption of alcohol.
You see, according to some reformers,
the main cause of the decline of
American society during this time was
Americans getting pickled on grandpa's
old cough medicine. You know what I
mean? Anyway, in 1826, middle-class
clergy and businessmen founded the
American Temperance Society, which aimed
to reform drunkenness among
working-class men. And so, you got all
those fancy, schmancy, wealthy middle
classers sitting around in their smoking
rooms deciding that all those drunken
workingclass jumps are the problem with
America. Now, to be fair, drunkenness
really was a problem among the working
class since it often caused strain on
their families, not to mention a decline
in productivity in factories and other
industrial type work. But even so, the
temperance movement was largely a
middleclass movement aimed at the lower
working class that was heavily
influenced by the second great awakening
emphasis on the evils of alcohol. Oh,
and by the way, if you want note guys to
follow along with this video and all my
videos, check that link in the
description. Anyway, the American
Temperance Society grew rapidly until
there were over 5,000 local chapters of
the organization spread throughout the
United States, though the majority of
them were located in the north. Now,
eventually, the work of this movement
and others like it resulted in
significant political ramifications. For
example, many northern factory owners
threw their support behind the
temperance movement since they believed
that the productivity of their factories
would increase if the working poor were
not constantly drunk off their ever
loving skunk. And so with that kind of
support, by the 1850s, a dozen states
had passed prohibition policies which
outlawed the production and sale of
alcohol. Now, these measures were loudly
rejected, especially by Irish and German
immigrant laborers. But for the most
part, they lacked the ability to vote
and therefore had no way to challenge
such policies. So instead, the Irish
workers in Maine protested prohibition
in the Portland rum riot of 1855. So
thousands gathered outside the building
where the main government was holding
all the illegal alcohol. And fearing the
rest of attitude of the crowd, the mayor
sent a militia which began firing into
the crowd. It resulted in one death and
many injuries, but the violent public
outcry against such heavy-handed tactics
forced Maine to repeal the prohibition
law the next year. Okay. Now, the second
social reform movement I want to mention
here is the multiplication of mental
hospitals. So, prior to this period,
people with mental health conditions
were either criminalized or made to
suffer social isolation because their
problems were not understood. But here's
where I introduce you to a lion of a
woman named Doroththia Dicks. So she got
real agitated by the plight of mentally
ill people, many of whom spent their
lives in dirty and unsanitary prisons as
if they were criminals. And so she got
busy reforming this injustice. She
traveled the country and spoke
vehemently about the need to treat
mentally ill people with dignity and
care. And as a result, many state
legislators approved funds to build or
refurbish mental hospitals where this
misunderstood population could receive
professional care instead of being
punished for a condition they could not
help. Okay, so now let's move on to
another category of reform that got
loads of traction during this period,
namely abolitionism, which describes
efforts to eradicate slavery in America.
And again, you don't have to go that far
to trace the roots of this movement to
the strong anti-slavery rhetoric pouring
forth from the anointed mouths of many
second grade awakening preachers.
Anyway, in the beginning, the cause of
abolition was mainly taken up by black
Americans themselves. Free blacks in the
northern states used all kinds of
methods to attack the system, including
lecture tours and assisting in the
resettlement of runaway enslaved people
and the publication of abolitionist
pamphlets. And one of the most famous
black pamphleteers during this period
was our boy David Walker. He was all
kinds of fiery and wrote essays like an
appeal to the colored citizens of the
world in which he argued for an
immediate abolition of slavery. And if
it was not done, then enslaved blacks
would emancipate themselves by force.
And such threats, not surprisingly, led
many paranoid southerners to clutch the
ever loving heck out of their pearls
since they were always on edge with the
fear of slave rebellions. But also in
1833, free black women joined with white
Quaker women to form the Philadelphia
Female Anti-Slavery Society. It was a
rare example of an interracial reform
movement and they organized boycots of
goods that were produced with enslaved
labor, most notably cotton. Now, over
time, many northern white folks joined
the abolitionist cause as well. And
probably the best example here is
William Lloyd Garrison. And Garrison had
precisely no chill regarding his
abolitionist principles. And he
channeled that lack of chill into what
would become a very popular abolitionist
newspaper known as the Liberator. In the
paper, Garrison and his crew drew
inspiration from black abolitionists
like David Walker and argued for
immediate emancipation without any
compensation to be granted to
slaveholders. But Garrison did not share
Walker's commitment to violence and
instead emphasized that even radical
abolition needed to occur by persuasion
or to use the vocabulary of the era
moral suag. Now, as a result of this
flurry of abolitionist ground pounding,
southern legislators in Congress got
real twitchy about this threat to their
way of life. Therefore, they pushed to
impose a gag rule in Congress that took
all debate about slavery off the table
for a period of time. And while that
rule did stifle congressional debate on
the issue, abolitionists outside the
halls of Congress kept cranking up the
volume on their descent. And perhaps
most eloquent of all dissenters was
Frederick Douglas, who had escaped
slavery in Maryland and settled in
Massachusetts. In 1845, he published a
memoir that told the story of his
enslavement titled A Narrative Life of
Frederick Douglas. And in it, he
recounted with deep eloquence the
brutality of his life under the
enslaver's lash. And so, having publicly
outed himself as a runaway, he migrated
to Great Britain for 2 years. And while
he was there, British abolitionist
purchased Douglas's freedom. So, he
returned to the United States, and with
his newly acquired freedom, gave
thousands of hours of lectures and even
published his own abolitionist
newspaper, The North Star. Now, let me
briefly tell you about the effects of
abolitionist efforts, and there are two
big ones. First, by 1820, all northern
states had either abolished slavery or
passed gradual emancipation laws. And by
1860, the north was entirely free of
enslaved people. And such a development
greatly increased the size of the free
black communities in the north. But then
the second effect was that southern
states made efforts to impose even
greater control over their enslaved
populations. Now to be fair, there was a
relatively small abolitionist sentiment
in the south that argued for gradual
emancipation. However, their arguments
were mainly motivated by the fear of
slave rebellions like the Haitian
Revolution and Nat Turner's rebellion
and certainly not the dignity and
humanity of enslaved blacks in their
midst. But for the most part, southern
abolitionists were dismissed and tighter
restrictions on black rights were
imposed. For example, states passed laws
making it illegal to free enslaved
people or to teach them to read and
write and prohibited marriage among the
enslaved, etc. Okay, now let's talk
about another big area of reform during
this period, namely women's rights. Now,
women played a significant role in the
abolitionist movement. However, it was
largely a male-led enterprise. And so,
that reality convinced some of these
women that the only way they could
actually give full expression to their
talents for reform is if they had equal
rights with the men folk. And this
movement erupted in full force in 1848
when Lucricia Ma and Elizabeth Katy
Stanton organized the Senica Falls
Convention with the express purpose of
organizing for women's rights. And under
their leadership, the convention drafted
a document codifying their desires known
as the Declaration of Sentiments and
Resolutions, which was cast in the form
of the Declaration of Independence and
said this, "We hold these truths to be
self-evident that all men and women are
created equal."
>> Oh, you saucy ladies. Anyway, it goes on
to list the grievances of women against
society that has repeatedly
disenfranchised them and treated them as
secondclass citizens. Now, their efforts
wouldn't bear the fullness of its fruit
for another 70 years or so, but this was
the first time when women planted their
flag in the ground and refused to give
up what was rightfully theirs. And
although this first iteration of the
women's rights movement was born out of
the abolitionist movement, the call for
women's rights was still during this
period focused on white women's rights.
Okay. The last category of reform you
need to know about is a couple of
significant movements toward religious
reform and that came in two distinct
flavors. The first flavor was the
multiplication of various utopian
societies. Now, by definition, a utopian
society reflects an impulse to reform
society not by directly engaging
existing social structures, but by
creating societies entirely separate
from the wider culture. And I'll give
you two examples. First was the Brook
Farm Community, which was founded in
1841 by George Ripley in Massachusetts.
And his effort was to create an
experiment in socialist living that was
influenced by French socialism. The idea
was that class division was tearing
apart the fabric of society. And
therefore, in the Brook Farm community,
Ripley abolished class structure and
each member contributed the work that
they were most interested in doing.
Additionally, the community promoted
equality between men and women while
focusing heavily on education and the
enlightenment of the mind of its
members. But as it turns out, grand
ideals still cost money and because the
community was never able to become
financially viable, it closed only 6
years after it began. But then a more
successful attempt at utopia was the
formation of the Onida community in
1848. Now its founder was a New York man
named John Humphrey Noise who himself
experienced a profound Christian
conversion under the preaching of
Charles Finny. And Noise developed a
novel belief that Jesus Christ had
already returned to earth in the first
century and therefore Christians were
able to usher in the perfection of the
kingdom of God on earth. In light of
that, all members of the community
surrendered their property to the
community and were encouraged to
practice complex marriage, which meant
that any consenting adult could uh
relate with any other consenting adult.
And while all that sounds all wow, so
much freedom and equality and stuff,
here's where I tell you that noise was
pretty dictatorial. Not so much about
the act of, you know, relating, but more
about the conception of children, which
required noise approval. So in the end,
the system of complex marriage turned
into more of a system of eugenics, which
sought to control the traits of the
Onidita population. Anyway, the
community lasted for about three decades
and then upon its dissolution, some of
the members of the community converted
it into a joint stock company that
focused on the manufacturer of
silverware. Oh, that's fun. Okay,
briefly, the second flavor of religious
reform during this period spawned
entirely new religious movements. And
here, let's meet the Mormons. So, do you
remember in the last video when we
talked about the burned over district in
New York, which was a hot bed for
Christian conversion during the Second
Great Awakening? Well, it just so
happened that a man by the name of
Joseph Smith experienced a profound
conversion in this area and later began
receiving religious visions of his own.
Now, the content of these visions
essentially centered on Jesus Christ
bemoning the corruption of his church in
America and that he had chosen Smith to
reform Christianity by establishing a
new church which became known as the
Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day
Saints. What you need to keep in mind is
that this was a thoroughly American
version of Christianity, not least
because Smith claimed that Christ had
visited North America after his
crucifixion. Regardless, the wider
Christian community of New York were not
fans of this upstart prophet and took
special umbrage with the Mormon doctrine
of polygamy. And such umbrage forced
Smith and his followers to flee to West
Illinois where he was eventually jailed
and killed. And at that the Mormon
community migrated westward to the
extreme isolation of the Utah territory
and under the leadership of Brigham
Young established a proper theocracy.
Okay, you can click here to watch my
other videos for unit 4 or you can click
here to grab my video note guides which
are going to help you get all the
contents of this course firmly crammed
into your brain fold. I'm glad you
dropped by and I'll catch you on the
flipflop. Himler out.